Guide to the Harry Hakam Papers ALBA.046
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Harry Hakam Papers
1937-1988
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Hakam, Harry, 1913-1996
ALBA.046
0.25 Linear Feet (1 box)
Harry Hakam (1913-1996) was an electrician and union activist who fought with the International Brigades in the Spanish Civil War as a machine-gunner, a runner, and an electrician, taking part in the Jarama, Brunete and Aragon offensives. The collection consists of materials dating from Hakam's time in Spain, including correspondence and propaganda graphics; as well as materials relating to post-Spanish Civil War political events in Spain, and the activities of Spanish Civil War veterans.
Provenance
The Harry Hakam Papers were donated to the Abraham Lincoln Brigade Archives in 1994 by Hakam's wife. This collection came to New York University in January 2001 as part of the original acquisition of ALBA collections, formerly housed at Brandeis University.
Access Restrictions
Materials are open to researchers. Please contact the Tamiment Library & Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives for more information and to schedule an appointment, tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu or 212-998-2630.
Historical/Biographical Note
Harry Hakam was born in Brooklyn, New York in 1913. His father was a building contractor. Hakam finished two years of college and three years of union courses in electrical engineering before sailing for Spain in February 1936. He was among the first Americans to join the International Brigades. In Spain, Hakam started out as a machine-gunner, then became a runner in a communications unit in the Abraham Lincoln Brigade, taking part in the Jarama, Brunete and Aragon offensives. Later Hakam worked in the rear as an electrician. Hakam (who signed some of his letters "Yog De Von"), stayed in Spain until the International Brigades evacuated in September of 1938.
In World War II, Hakam was a frogman in the U.S. Navy, and afterward he continued a career as a journeyman electrician and union activist. He died in 1996.
Scope and Content Note
Series I: Spanish Civil War, 1937-1939. All of Hakam's letters and postcards in this series, some written by candlelight from a dugout, date from his early months in Spain; all are typed copies of the originals. In the letters Hakam recounts tales from his arrival in Paris and his travels through southern France on the way to Spain. He describes a spirited variety show performed by his group, the "Convulsionaries of Brooklyn," for townspeople in Albacete and other Spanish towns. Other notable items in this series include a press release for a celebration by the Friends of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade for American prisoners recently released from prison in Spain, which includes summaries of speeches by several of the released prisoners, among others; propaganda graphics, including a paper fold-in game that converts diagrams of pigs into a portrait of Hitler; and a lighter made with a braided rope wick.
Series II: Subject Files, 1961-1988. This series consists of materials relating to post-Spanish Civil War political events in Spain, and the activities of Spanish Civil War veterans. Of note is a 1961 Life Magazine article featuring a photograph of Hakam taken in Spain; and a playbill from a Lincoln Center fiftieth anniversary tribute to American veterans of the Spanish Civil War. Many of the articles and other materials about Spanish politics and the veterans' return visits to Spain are in Spanish and Catalan.
Arrangement
Folders are arranged alphabetically.
The files are grouped into two series:
Missing Title
I, Spanish Civil War, 1937-1939
II, Subject Files, 1961-1988
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Marjorie Polon Papers, ALBA #159.
ALBA collections at the Tamiment Library.
Separated Material
Photographs from the Harry Hakam Papers have been transferred to the non-print section of the ALBA collection in the Tamiment Library (ALBA Photo #36).
Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Participation, American.; Printed ephemera.; Correspondence.; Articles.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Personal narratives.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939.; Partido Comunista de España; Partit del Treball de Catalunya; Juventud Socialista Unificada; Spain. Ejercito Popular de la Republica. Abraham Lincoln Battalion; Friends of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade; Spain. Ejercito Popular de la Republica. Brigada Internacional, XV; Hakam, Harry, 1913-1996; Spain. Ejército Popular de la República. Brigada Internacional, XV--Biography; Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade
- Series I: Spanish Civil War, 1937-1939.
  - As War's End Nears in Spain (article), 1937-02-01-1937-04-30 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence: Hakam, Harry to Al Erdberg, 1938-10 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Friends of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade: Welcome Home Celebration to Honor Released Prisoners (press release), 1938 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Juventud Socialista Unificado (JSU): Second Anniversary Publication, ca.1937 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Rope Lighter, ca.1937 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Spanish Civil War: Graphics, 1937-1939 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Series II: Subject Files, 1961-1988.
  - Associació Catalana d'Ex-Presos Polítics i Socials: Conference Publication, Jun 1977 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Coordinadora Catalana d'Associacions d'Ex-Combatents de la Republica: Fiftieth Annivesary Program, Oct 1988 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - El Camino del Dolor y del Honor, Emilio Peydio (typescript), Jul 1976 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Exports from Russia: Subversion and Riots, Life Magazine (article, with picture of Hakam), Oct 1961 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Fiftieth Annivesary of the Spanish Civil War: Lincoln Center Tribute Program and Stickers (Spanish), Apr 1986 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Kramer, Jacob (article about), Mar 1982 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Partido Comunista de España (PCE) and Partit del Treball de Catalunya (PTC) (flyers), undated, ca.1979 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Prisoners of the Good Fight, by Carl Geiser: Research Memo and Promotional Flyer, 1981, ca.1986 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Veterans: Return Visits to Spain (articles), Oct 1986, Oct. 1988 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Veterans: Return Visits to Spain: Itinerary and Contact Information, Oct 1986 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade (memos and articles), Nov 1980-Nov-82 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Wellman, Saul: "Jewish Vets of the Spanish Civil War" (article), Jan 1973 (Box 1, Folder 18)